{"tossups": [{"question": "George Miller\u2019s work on this process and its \u201cmagic number\u201d was criticized by later experiments that demonstrated the value of \u201cchunking\u201d in this process. The ancient Greek and Roman \u201cmethod of loci\u201d was used to improve this process, and autistic savants are frequently mentioned for their ability to perform extreme feats of this process. For ten points, name this mental process that consists of encoding, storing, and retrieving information about past events.", "answer": "<b> memory</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {}, {"question": "One of these policies named for Walker improved relations with Great Britain after the repeal of the Corn Laws. One of these policies was described as an abomination and led to the Nullification Crisis, while the Smoot-Hawley example made the Great Depression worse by slowing global trade. NAFTA restricts Canada, Mexico, and the United States from using, for ten points, what type of tax on imported goods?", "answer": "<b> tariff</b> (accept Walker<b> Tariff</b>,<b> Tariff</b> of Abominations,<b> Smoot-Hawley</b> Tariff)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "With Johanna Bethune and Isabella Graham, this man\u2019s wife co-founded an organization that is now Graham Windham, a youth-focused non-profit; this man\u2019s wife also assisted Dolley Madison with finding funds for the Washington Monument. For ten points, name this husband of Elizabeth Schuyler [skyler], an American founding father whose biographer, Ron Chernow, inspired Lin-Manuel Miranda to write a Broadway musical.", "answer": "Alexander<b> Hamilton</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Sultanate of Rum failed to stop this campaign, in part because the Danishmends had tied up the forces of Alp Arslan. Peter the Hermit inspired the poor to aid this campaign, whose participants rallied around the the cry \u201cDeus vult!\u201d Following the Battle of Manzikert, Alexius Comnemnus was forced to request this campaign to counteract the power of the Seljuk Turks. Pope Urban II\u2019s Council of Clermont began, for ten points, what Christian campaign that retook Jerusalem from the Muslims in 1099?", "answer": "<b> First Crusade</b> (prompt on Crusade(s)) <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One holder of this position fought the Battle of Reed Rules in order to eliminate the disappearing quorum. The longest holder of this position was Sam Rayburn, and the only holder of this position to later become President has been James Polk. This position controls appointments to the Rules Committee and is second in the presidential succession. Nancy Pelosi was the first female holder of, for ten points, what political position, currently held by Paul Ryan, that leads the lower house of U.S. Congress?", "answer": "<b> Speaker</b> of the U.S. House of Representatives", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This city was ruled by dual kings from the Agiad and Eurypontid dynasties, who were responsible to the ephors. One ruler of this city, Lycurgus the Lawgiver, introduced the agoge [ah-goh-gah], a rigorous training program for all young men. One king of this city replied \u201ccome and take them\u201d after being asked to lay down his arms by Xerxes I. Leonidas died at Thermopylae with 300 soldiers from, for ten points, what militaristic Greek city-state, a rival of Athens?", "answer": "<b> Sparta</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This artist created a work inspired by Goya\u2019s<em> 3rd of May, 1808</em> showing pregnant women with children in front of a futuristic firing squad; that work was a response to U.S. involvement in the Korean War. Another work by this artist includes a flower growing from a sword held in a severed arm. A screaming horse stands under a light bulb in that monochrome work by this artist. For ten points, name this Cubist painter who depicted the bombing of a Basque town during the Spanish Civil War in<em> Guernica</em>.", "answer": "Pablo Ruiz y<b> Picasso</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This ruler was able to lift trading restrictions after signing the Treaty of K\u00a8u\u00b8c\u00a8uk Kaynarca [koo-chook kai-nar-ka]. This ruler descended from the royal family of Anhalt and founded the Hermitage. Cossacks targeted this patron of Voltaire during Pugachev\u2019s Rebellion. Fake villages to show prosperity were constructed by this ruler\u2019s lover, Grigory Potemkin. For ten points, name this enlightened despot and 18th century Empress of Russia.", "answer": "<b> Catherine the Great</b> (or<b> Catherine II</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this decade, the Emergency Tariff and Fordney-McCuber Tariff were passed to support American agriculture. Charles Lindbergh flew<em> The Spirit of St. Louis</em> during this decade, which began with the passage of the 19th Amendment and included the Harlem Renaissance. For ten points, name this decade of American prosperity, often described by the phrase \u201cRoaring,\u201d that was ended by a Wall Street crash on Black Tuesday.", "answer": "19<b>20s</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>One island in this territory was home to a naval bombing range that, after the death of David Sanes, was closed after protests in 2003. Vieques is a part of this region, whose</b> <b>El Yunque rainforest is home to the (+)</b> <b>coqui frog. Its governor lives in La Fortaleza, a</b> <b>converted fortress built in 1540 under the orders of Charles V. Residents of this territory were (*) </b> granted US citizenship in the Jones Act and endorsed changing their official status in a two-part 2012 referendum. For ten points, name this Spanish-speaking US commonwealth whose capital is San Juan.", "answer": "<b> Puerto Rico</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. Samuel DuPont chaired a commission that planned this strategy. The</b><em><b> H. L. Hunley</b></em><b>, the first submarine to sink another ship, did so while opposing this</b> <b>strategy. David Farragut said \u201cDamn the (+)</b> <b>torpedoes, full speed ahead\u201d to capture the</b> <b>port of Mobile as part of this strategy. Raphael Semmes proposed swift runners to defeat this strategy and bring (*) </b> cotton to Bermuda. For ten points, name this strategy, a part of the Union\u2019s Anaconda Plan that prevented the Confederacy from conducting overseas trade.", "answer": "Union<b> blockade</b> (accept<b> Anaconda Plan</b> before mention)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In this novel, a character describes the Seven Years War as over \u201ca few acres of snow somewhere around Canada.\u201d The title character of this work travels with the aforementioned Martin and the valet (+) Cacambo, with whom he takes sheep laden with gems away from El Dorado. The title character is advised by a syphilitic philosopher who, despite the Great (*)</b> Lisbon Earthquake, is convinced he lives in the \u201cbest of all possible worlds.\u201d Pangloss and Cunegonde are characters in, for ten points, what satirical novel written by Voltaire?", "answer": "<b> Candide</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>This leader employed Nikolai Yezhov as the head of a secret police force and approved Lavrentiy Beria\u2019s plan to kill thousands of dissidents in what is now called the Katyn massacre. This leader may have responded to a rebellion against him by orchestrating a mass (+) famine in Ukraine, the Holodomor. Hundreds of thousands of political opponents, including fellow (*) </b> Communists, were killed in a Great Purge ordered by this leader from 1936 to 1938. For ten points, name this dictator of the USSR who ruled during World War II.", "answer": "Joseph<b> Stalin</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The shooting of Isao Oyama outside this city\u2019s Hongqiao Airport sparked an attack on</b> <b>this city. The Gang of Four included Mao Zedong\u2019s wife and (+)</b> <b>three party leaders from</b> <b>this city, which the Japanese sieged for three months in autumn (*)</b> 1937. For ten points, name this city on the mouth of the Yangtze River on the East China Sea, whose 24 million inhabitants rival Guangzhou, Shenzhen, and Beijing as China\u2019s most populous city.", "answer": "<b> Shanghai</b> Page 8", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Luis Carrero Blanco was murdered in this country, where King (*) </b> Juan Carlos I reigned for four decades. For ten points, name this European country where the ETA seeks Basque independence from a country led from Madrid.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Spain</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This diplomat re-assigned Archer Blood within his department, rather than respond to the Blood Telegram warning of genocide during the Bangladesh War. This Cabinet member</b> <b>began the policy of d\u00b4etente with the (+)</b> <b>USSR and worked to normalize relations with</b> <b>China. This man was co-recognized with Le Duc Tho for their work on the Paris Peace Accords; Le Duc Tho refused that Nobel Peace Prize, as the (*)</b> Vietnam War had not actually ended. For ten points, name this Secretary of State under Presidents Nixon and Ford.", "answer": "Henry<b> Kissinger</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One opera set in this country includes an offstage chorus singing Psalm 104 and is the final entry in the \u201cPortrait Trilogy.\u201d Another opera set in this country was commissioned by Ismail Pasha to celebrate the opening of the Khedival Opera House and features the</b> <b>title princess singing (+)</b> <b>\u201cO patria mia.\u201d This country is the setting of a Philip Glass</b> <b>opera about a pioneering monotheistic ruler and a Verdi opera in which the title princess is buried alive with (*)</b> Radames. For ten points, name this ancient civilization, the setting of<em> Aida</em> and <em>Akhnaten</em>.", "answer": "(ancient)<b> Egypt</b>  (1) <b>Control of this modern-day country was established after the 1806 Battle of</b> <b>Blaauwberg. The Jameson Raid attempted to provoke a rebellion in this modern day</b> <b>country, where the (+)</b> <b>Great Trek led to the foundation of the Orange Free State.</b> <b>The British drove Dutch settlers out of this country over the course of two (*)</b> Boer Wars. Cecil Rhodes founded the de Beers company to mine diamonds from Kimberley in, for ten points, what African country where the British established a colony at Cape Town? ANSWER: Republic of<b> South Africa</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}], "bonuses": []}